Finding Aid for Arvid Jouppi Papers, 1940-1987 (bulk 1963-1987)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arvid Jouppi Papers 1940-1987, 1963-1987
Jouppi, Arvid
24 linear feet
Detroit, Michigan, businessman, researcher and analyst of the automotive and related industry; papers include correspondence, topical files, and other material documenting his Wall Street career and his management of Arvid Jouppi Associates.
89162 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mr. Jouppi in June 1987. (Donor no. 7454 )
The collection is open for research.
Arvid Jouppi, internationally-known specialist in the automobile and related industries, was born in Kaleva, Michigan, on March 14, 1918, of Finnish parents. He attended what is now Michigan State University and received his B.A. degree in 1940.uring World War II, Jouppi served as captain in the Marine Corps and became one of the few specialists in electronic countermeasures. He flew 35 combat missions and received the Distinguished Flying Cross. He also continued his education, as a special student at Harvard University and by enrolling in correspondence courses in mathematics from the University of Wisconsin.
During World War II, Jouppi served as captain in the Marine Corps and became one of the few specialists in electronic countermeasures. He flew 35 combat missions and received the Distinguished Flying Cross. He also continued his education, as a special student at Harvard University and by enrolling in correspondence courses in mathematics from the University of Wisconsin.
After the war, Jouppi spent several years as news editor in the Detroit Bureau of the Associated Press (AP). The automobile industry was one of the major areas of coverage for the bureau, and it was at that time that Jouppi's interest in automobile-related matters was sparked. In addition, he continued his studies by enrolling as a special student at the University of Michigan graduate school of engineering. He left the AP in 1947 to join the Sperry Gyroscope Company as an engineering supervisor and as editor of the Sperry Engineering Review. He remained at Sperry for five years.
In 1952, Jouppi began his long association with the automobile industry when he joined General Motors Corporation as a central staff executive. He developed and served as editor of the GM Engineering Journal and later worked in college and university relations. Jouppi left GM to work at Chrysler Corporation in December 1957, serving initially as assistant director of investor relations and later as interim manager of plant and community relations activities. Jouppi then moved from Detroit to New York to become Chrysler's director of public and investor relations activities in the eastern United States. In his position he worked closely with many firms on Wall Street as Chrysler stock became one of the most actively traded on the stock exchange.
Jouppi's experience in the automobile industry and knowledge of investment practices led him to join Hayden, Stone Incorporated, a major Wall Street brokerage firm, in 1963. He first worked as senior analyst of the automotive, truck, rubber fabricating, automotive parts, and farm machinery fields. One year later he was designated a member of the Research Operations Committee. He was elected vice president in 1966 and assumed management of the firm's retail research activities. In that position, he supervised the budgeting, staffing, programming, and execution of research services for 1100 Hayden, Stone account executives, and an additional 300 executives in correspondent firms. Throughout his tenure at Hayden, Stone, Jouppi arranged forums, or discussion groups, of area financial and industrial leaders, a practice he would continue throughout his career and which would become a trademark of his.
In 1970, Jouppi was elected to the Board of Directors of Hayden, Stone at a time when the firm was experiencing serious financial difficulties. He worked very hard to save the company, including the investment of a large amount of his own funds, but was unable to do so. In September of that year, Hayden, Stone was taken over by the firm of Cogan, Berlind, Weill and Levitt, and Jouppi's own assets were seriously depleted.
After the closing of Hayden, Stone, Jouppi immediately went to work for the Detroit research services firm of William C. Roney and Company, as vice president and director of research. He remained for a year but desired to return to Wall Street. In 1971, therefore, he joined the firm of Delafield Childs, Inc., a Wall Street institutional research servicing firm, as vice president, supervisory analyst, and specialist in the automobile industry. He eventually became a senior vice president and member of the executive planning committee. He remained with the firm until January 1975, at which time he left to establish his own research services firm, Arvid Jouppi Associates (AJA), located outside of Detroit, Michigan.
One of Jouppi's maxims for many years has been that research is critically important to insuring sound financial investments. As head of AJA, his time is devoted, in large part, to automobile-related financial research. He works on a fee basis for companies, fiduciary firms, and governmental agencies, and at times has been affiliated with and worked on a commission basis for various Wall Street firms, including Colin, Hochstin Company, John Muir and Company, and Keane Securities Company, Inc. Because of his extensive experience in studying the automobile industry and his easy accessibility, both the printed and electronic media have turned to him for insight and analysis. He has appeared regularly on the major television and radio networks and is frequently cited in the financial and business sections of leading newspapers.
Jouppi's personal and professional lives revolve around his devout Christianity. He is a member of the Peace Lutheran Church in Detroit, where he has taught Sunday School for many years, and is a financial advisor and trustee to the Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod Foundation. He also serves on the board of directors of Suomi College, and has long been affiliated with Gideons International.
Jouppi was married for many years to the former Marjorie Kline. She died of Parkinson's Disease in 1986. They had four children: Mary (Mrs. Paul Marquis), William, James, and Gloria. In 1987, Jouppi was remarried to Edith Lumley.
The Arvid Jouppi Papers (24 linear feet) are primarily comprised of materials which document his Wall Street career and his management of Arvid Jouppi Associates. There are only limited materials related to his professional life prior to his tenure at Hayden, Stone. The collection is particularly strong in documenting the everyday work, research findings, and economic philosophy of one of Wall Street's leading automobile industry analysts; the difficulties, at times, of developing and running an independent research services firm (AJA); and the economic vicissitudes of the fields, particularly the automotive field, in which Jouppi was interested and conducted research.
The Jouppi Papers came to the Bentley Historical Library with only minimal arrangement. The papers had been transferred between Jouppi's offices and home several times and much of the original order of the materials was lost in the process. What remained were materials roughly arranged by chronological stage of Jouppi's professional career. That order has been retained. The papers consist of seven series: Personal; Chronological; Early Career; Hayden, Stone; William C. Roney and Company; Delafield Childs, Inc.; Arvid Jouppi Associates; and Writings. For each series in which there is a correspondence subseries, the correspondence is both incoming and outgoing unless otherwise noted on the contents list, and chronological files of correspondence are arranged by month and year. For each series in which there is a topical subseries, the files are arranged alphabetically.
Subjects:
Arvid Jouppi Associates.; Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Automobile industry and trade--Japan.; Businessmen--Religious life.; Delafield Childs, Inc.; Hayden, Stone & Co.; Suomi College.; Wall Street.; Wm. C. Roney & Co.
- Personal
  The Personal series (1 linear foot) is comprised of two subseries: Topical and Correspondence. It is the series to which the researcher should turn to become familiar with the many stages of Jouppi's professional career, and with the two most important influences on the course of his life, his family and his religious beliefs. Without an appreciation of the latter, the researcher cannot understand what motivated Jouppi in arriving at major decisions.
  - Topical Files
    The Topical subseries includes Biographical files which contain fairly detailed materials to assist the researcher in determining the major events in Jouppi's life. Materials in the ISSOF Associates and Jouppi Management Company files pertain to the family real estate and mineral rights companies. The Job Searches file contains correspondence and resumes which are valuable in detailing Jouppi's skills and those business areas in which he thought his talents could best be used. The Organizations files document his devotion to both Suomi College and to the Lutheran Church and his involvement, as trustee and president, with the Lutheran Church - Missouri Synod Foundation. The Prayers and Personal Reflections file includes prayers written by Jouppi which demonstrate his strong reliance on God for guidance in daily affairs.
    - Biographical, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
      (mostly black and white, formal portraits of Jouppi)
    - Financial 1964-1973 (Box 1)
      (includes materials re: loans, stock holdings, assets, earnings)
    - Income Taxes 1975, 1982 (Box 1)
    - ISSOF Associates 1976-1985 (Box 1)
      (includes financial materials, minutes of meetings)
    - Job Searches (Box 1)
      (includes correspondence and resumes primarily re:1957 and 1963)
      (see also Personal, Correspondence files)
    - Jouppi Management Company (Box 1)
      (includes financial reports)
    - Kiwanis Club (Box 1)
      (includes materials re: newsletter edited by Jouppi)
    - Military Service (Box 1)
      (includes materials re: awards/distinctions)
    - Oldsmobile Restoration Project: materials re: Jouppi's car 1983 (Box 1)
    - Organizations
      - Lutheran Church-Missouri Synod Foundation, 1970s (Box 1)
      - Peace Lutheran Church, Detroit, Michigan
        - General 1969-1982 (Box 1)
          (mostly Sunday School materials)
        - Stewardship Committee: minutes 1976-1981 (Box 1)
          (with gaps)
      - Suomi College 1970-1985 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Prayers and Personal Reflections (Box 1)
    - Priorities (list and letter from daughter) 1981 (Box 1)
    - Road Racing Drivers Club: newsletters, edited by Jouppi 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries is divided into chronological and alphabetical files. It is particularly enlightening regarding Jouppi's relationships with his four children.
    - Chronological
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - 1940-1959 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980- (Box 1)
    - Alphabetical
      - Aquaviva, Mike (Box 1)
      - Browning, Zora (Box 1)
      - Cox, Larry: publication of Cox paper (Box 1)
      - Jouppi children: outgoing letters addressed to all four children (Box 1)
      - Jouppi, James (Box 1)
      - Jouppi, Mary: 1 outgoing letter1969 (Box 1)
- Chronological
  The Chronological series (11 linear feet) is comprised of materials generated by Jouppi, which he maintained in separate files arranged chronologically by year and month. Included are correspondence (mostly outgoing) and reports, primarily related to Jouppi's professional career, and miscellaneous materials which are of a personal nature. The files are nearly complete for the years 1966-1987. They provide valuable details regarding Jouppi's research activities and offer great insight into his personality. Because of their completeness, they should be studied prior to reviewing those series which pertain to individual phases of Jouppi's professional career.
  - 1966
    - January-April (Box 2)
    - May-August (Box 2)
    - September-December (Box 2)
  - 1967
    - January-April (Box 2)
    - May-September (Box 2)
  - 1968
    - January-February (Box 2)
    - March-April (Box 2)
    - May (Box 2)
    - June (Box 2)
    - July-August (Box 2)
    - September (Box 2)
    - October (Box 2)
    - November-December (Box 2)
  - 1969
    - June-October (Box 2)
    - November-December (Box 3)
  - 1970
    - January-February (Box 3)
    - March (Box 3)
    - April (Box 3)
    - May-June (Box 3)
    - July-August (Box 3)
    - September-December (Box 3)
  - 1971
    - January-February (Box 3)
    - March (Box 3)
    - April-May (Box 3)
    - June (Box 3)
    - July (Box 3)
    - August-September (Box 3)
    - October (Box 3)
    - November (Box 4)
    - December (Box 4)
  - 1972
    - January (Box 4)
    - February (Box 4)
    - March (Box 4)
    - April (Box 4)
    - May (Box 4)
    - June (Box 4)
    - July (Box 4)
    - August (Box 4)
    - September (Box 4)
    - October (Box 4)
    - November-December (Box 4)
  - 1973
    - January (Box 4)
    - February (Box 5)
    - March (Box 5)
    - April (Box 5)
    - May-June (Box 5)
    - July-August (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November-December (Box 5)
  - 1974
    - January (Box 5)
    - February-March (Box 5)
    - April-May (Box 5)
    - June (Box 5)
    - July-August (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November (Box 5)
    - December (Box 5)
  - 1975
    - January (Box 5)
    - February (Box 5)
    - March (Box 5)
    - April (Box 5)
    - May (Box 5)
    - June (Box 5)
    - July (Box 5)
    - August (Box 5)
    - September (Box 5)
    - October (Box 5)
    - November (Box 6)
    - December (Box 6)
  - 1976
    - January (Box 6)
    - February (Box 6)
    - March (Box 6)
    - April (Box 6)
    - May (Box 6)
    - June (Box 6)
    - July (Box 6)
    - August (Box 6)
    - September (Box 6)
    - October-December (Box 6)
      (mostly November)
  - 1977
    - January (Box 6)
    - February (Box 6)
    - March (Box 6)
    - April (Box 6)
    - May (Box 6)
    - June-July (Box 6)
    - August (Box 6)
    - September-October (Box 6)
    - November (Box 6)
    - December (Box 6)
  - 1978
    - January (Box 6)
    - February (Box 6)
    - March-April (Box 6)
    - May-June (Box 6)
    - July-August (Box 6)
    - September-October (Box 6)
    - November (Box 6)
    - December (Box 6)
  - 1979
    - January (Box 6)
    - February-March (Box 7)
    - April (Box 7)
    - May-June (Box 7)
    - July (Box 7)
    - August (Box 7)
    - September-October (Box 7)
    - November (Box 7)
    - December (Box 7)
  - 1980
    - January (Box 7)
    - February, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - March (Box 7)
    - April-May (Box 7)
    - June (Box 7)
    - August (Box 7)
    - September (Box 7)
    - October (Box 7)
    - November-December (Box 7)
  - 1981
    - May (Box 7)
    - August (Box 7)
  - 1982
    - March (Box 7)
    - April (Box 7)
    - May (Box 7)
    - June (Box 7)
    - July (Box 7)
    - August (Box 7)
    - September (Box 7)
    - October (Box 8)
    - November (Box 8)
  - 1983
    - January (Box 8)
    - February (Box 8)
    - March, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - April (Box 8)
    - May (Box 8)
    - June (Box 8)
    - July (Box 8)
    - August (Box 8)
    - September (Box 8)
    - October (Box 8)
    - November (Box 8)
    - December (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
      (1 of 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
      (2 of 2)
  - 1984
    - January (Box 9)
    - February (Box 9)
    - March (Box 9)
    - April (Box 9)
    - May (Box 9)
    - June (Box 9)
    - July (Box 9)
    - August (Box 9)
    - September (Box 9)
    - October (Box 9)
    - November (Box 9)
    - December (Box 9)
  - 1985
    - January (Box 9)
    - February, 1 folders (Box 9)
    - February, 1 folders (Box 10)
    - March (Box 10)
    - April (Box 10)
    - May (Box 10)
    - June (Box 10)
    - July, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - August (Box 10)
    - September, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - October, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - November, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - December, 1 folders (Box 10)
    - December, 1 folders (Box 11)
  - 1986
    - January (Box 11)
    - February (Box 11)
    - March (Box 11)
    - April (Box 11)
    - May, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - June (Box 11)
    - July (Box 11)
    - August (Box 11)
    - September (Box 11)
    - October (Box 11)
    - November (Box 11)
    - December (Box 12)
  - 1987
    - January (Box 12)
      (includes December 1986 items)
    - February (Box 12)
    - March (Box 12)
    - April (Box 12)
    - May (Box 12)
    - June (Box 12)
- Early Career
  The Early Career series (2 folders) contains materials related to Jouppi's employment with Sperry Gyroscope Company and Chrysler Corporation. They are mostly correspondence and clippings, but there are interesting notes and memoranda prepared by Jouppi regarding the conduct of his Chrysler investor relations work.
  - Chrysler (Box 12)
  - Sperry Gyroscope (Box 12)
- Hayden, Stone
  The Hayden, Stone series (2.5 linear feet) pertains to Jouppi's employment with the firm, which lasted from 1963-1970. For the first three years he was with the firm, he was responsible for monitoring activity in the automobile industry for the research department. Much of the materials from those years are comprised of the reports which he generated. The materials from the later years of this subseries document Jouppi's administrative duties (he was made second vice president of research in 1966 and was appointed head of the research department in April of 1969), as well as his continuing research activities.
  The series is divided into three subseries: Administrative, Topical, and Correspondence. The strength of both the Administrative and Topical subseries lies in the materials from which the researcher can study the activities of the research department of a major Wall Street brokerage firm, and through Jouppi, gain insight into possible reasons for its takeover by another firm. Particularly valuable are the Interoffice Communications files and Research Department file in the Administrative subseries and the Reports files in the Topical subseries. In addition, the researcher can study major trends in the automobile and related industries and determine how Wall Street viewed and reacted to them.
  - Administrative records
    - Interoffice Communications
      (includes meeting notes, progress flashes, and memos)
      - 1963-1966 (Box 13)
      - 1967 (Box 13)
      - 1968 (Box 13)
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - 1970, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Itinerary and Work Plans 1966-1970 (Box 13)
    - Organizational Chart 1967 (Box 13)
    - Organizational Changes: memos 1970 (Box 13)
    - Personnel Requisition Forms 1970 (Box 13)
      (completed)
    - Research Department: ideas, comments, budgets, staff, salaries 1968-1969 (Box 13)
    - Research Policy Committee 1969-1970 (Box 13)
    - Salary Administration (Box 13)
  - Topical
    - Agribusiness Council 1968 (Box 13)
    - Analyst Examination 1965 (Box 13)
      (includes Jouppi's results)
    - Bisgier vs. Fotomat
      - General 1969-1974 (Box 13)
      - Deposition 1974, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Citrus Industry: Jouppi report 1967 (Box 13)
    - Companies
      - 1965
        - Rockwell Standard Corporation (Box 13)
        - Stewart-Warner (Box 13)
      - 1966
        - Automobile Manufacturers Association (Box 13)
        - Brunswick (Box 13)
        - John Deere (Box 13)
        - Mack Truck (Box 13)
        - Massey Ferguson (Box 14)
        - North American Rockwell (Box 14)
      - 1967
        - Chrysler Corporation (Box 14)
      - 1968
        - American Motors (Box 14)
        - Burlington Industries (Box 14)
      - 1969
        - CBK Agronomics (Box 14)
          (includes 1970)
        - Cowles Communication (Box 14)
        - Harvard Industries (Box 14)
        - Neuro-Data (Box 14)
      - 1970
        - Slick Corporation (Box 14)
    - Computers in Research Department 1968-1969 (Box 14)
      (chiefly memos)
    - Computer Book: correspondence regarding (Box 14)
    - Containerization 1968 (Box 14)
    - Forums
      - Automobile Related Workshop 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 14)
        (mostly worksheets prepared by Jouppi for workshop
      - World Food Sufficiency
        - 1967 (Box 14)
          (includes proceedings)
        - 1968 (Box 14)
    - Reports
      - Automobile and Related Industries, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Automobile Parts Study 1966 (Box 14)
      - Board of Directors: reports prepared by Jouppi and others for Hayden, Stone Board 1964-1970 (Box 14)
      - Client Company: research briefs, projections and/or statistical data 1965-1966 (Box 14)
      - Investment Research Department: research briefs, projections, and/or statistical data prepared for the department
        - 1963 (Box 14)
        - 1964 (Box 14)
        - 1965 (Box 14)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 14)
        - 1969-1970 (Box 15)
      - Special
        - "A Candid Description of Some Research Unhappiness," 1967 (Box 15)
        - "Concerning the Capital Crunch-From Main Street to Wall Street," 1970 (Box 15)
        - "Constructive Responses to Stress," 1969 (Box 15)
        - "Discussion Notes on Investment Outlook for Auto and Auto related Equities," 1966 (Box 15)
        - "A Look at New Car Model Changeover Time" (Box 15)
        - "A Special Report to Research Officers," 1970 (Box 15)
        - "A Synopsis of Hayden, Stone Views on Auto Industry, Viewed at March 19, 1970" (Box 15)
        - "A White Paper on Hayden, Stone Research Describing 1959-1969 and Looking with Hope to 1969-1979" (Box 15)
    - Vietnam Trip 1968 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence
    The Correspondence subseries covers a variety of topics related to Hayden, Stone affairs and should be used to supplement the other two subseries. It is divided into two categories, Chronological and Personal. Jouppi kept a separate folder of correspondence labeled Personal, but which appears to be business related and is arranged chronologically by year and month. Interoffice memoranda are included in this folder.
    - Chronological
      - 1963-1966 (Box 15)
      - 1967 (Box 15)
      - 1968 (Box 15)
      - 1969 (Box 15)
      - 1970 (Box 15)
    - Personal (Box 15)
- William C. Roney & Co
  The William C. Roney and Company series (.5 linear feet) covers the period September 1970, to late November 1971, when Jouppi was employed as vice president and director of research. The quantity of materials reflects the limited tenure of his stay. The papers are divided into three subseries: Administrative, Topical, and Correspondence. Jouppi's administrative planning and organizing activities at Roney can be traced from the Administrative subseries and from Report files in the Topical subseries. The researcher will find Jouppi's outlines of plans for organizing his sector of the company and for broadening his client base, as well as his proposals for structuring the entire Roney organization. Those interested in the automobile industry will find 1971 industry analyses prepared by Jouppi. The Correspondence subseries concerns various business-related matters.
  - Administrative
    - Delegation of Tasks: proposed by Jouppi 1970 (Box 15)
    - Interoffice memoranda regarding salaries and Wm. C. Roney business 1970-1971 (Box 15)
    - Organization Roster 1971 (Box 15)
    - Preliminary Work Plan 1971 (Box 15)
      (mostly memos)
    - Research issues 1970-1971 (Box 15)
      (chiefly internal memoranda)
  - Topical
    - Christiana Securities vs. U.S. 1971
      - General (Box 15)